Guide to the Abbott Lowell Cummings Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Abbott Lowell Cummings papers
1956-1991
MS 1713
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(5 boxes and 1 audiocassette)
The papers consist primarily of student research papers, photocopies of public records, and reports on historic homes of Connecticut. Files on seventeenth century domestic architecture and on one home in Massachusettes are also included. Many of the papers and reports were completed by students in Cummings's architecture history classes at Yale University, but several reports were written by Cummings.
Cummings, Abbott Lowell, 1923-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the History of Art Department, 1996.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in two sections: Seventeenth Century Domestic Architecture and Research and project files on historic homes.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Original student papers in box 3 are restricted until January 1, 2067. Patrons must use the redacted versions of the papers in box 6.
Biographical / Historical
Abbott Lowell Cummings, noted authority on American architecture, received his B.A. from Oberlin College in 1945, and his Ph.D. from Ohio State University in 1950. In 1955 he became assistant director of the Society for the Preservation of New England Antiquities. He remained with the Society until December, 1983, eventually becoming executive director. In 1984 he became the Charles F. Montgomery Professor of American Decorative Arts at Yale University. He retired and achieved emeritus status in 1992.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist primarily of student research papers, photocopies of public records, and reports on historic homes of Connecticut. Files on seventeenth century domestic architecture and on one home in Massachusettes are also included. Many of the papers and reports were completed by students in Cummings's architecture history classes at Yale University, but several reports were written by Cummings.
Architecture, Domestic -- Connecticut; Historic buildings -- Conservation and restoration; Historic buildings -- Connecticut; Cummings, Abbott Lowell, 1923-; Yale University -- Faculty
- Seventeenth Century Domestic Architecture course, History of Art (student notebooks), 1986-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-17)
- Research and project files on historic homes
  - Connecticut, general, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Printed material (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Carpenter's Gothic in Southern Connecticut", 1982
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Material restricted until January 1, 2067 as established by Yale Corporation regulations. See redacted use copy.
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Branford
    - Probate records
      Scope and Contents
      These records consist mainly of photocopies of probate documents.
      - 1802-1815, Circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
      - 1758-1769, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 1720-1730, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - "A Rural Connecticut Town During the Federal Period: An Analysis of Branford, Conn. Probate Records (1802-1815)", 1989
        - Original (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 242-250 East Main Street: Tyler House, 1989
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 112 West Main Street: Nathaniel Harrison House (also known as Swain-Harrison House) (Box 2, Folder 3)
      General
      Microfiche of correspondence concerning house, 1940-1973.
      - Oversized material, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Warham Williams House (moved to Roxbury, Connecticut in the 1970s), 1988
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bridgeport, 266-268 Brewster Street: John Wheeler House, Circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Additional material (original), 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
    - Additional material (use copy), 1984-1989 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
    - Oversized material, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Brookfield, Iron Works Tavern (moved to Danbury, Connecticut), 1984
    - Original (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - East Haddam, Wickham Road: "The Mowings", 1984
    - Original (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Fair Haven, 500-502 Chapel Street, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fairfield, 1520 Bronson Road: Ogden House, 1985
    - Original (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Oversized material, Circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Greenwich, 39 Strickland Road (Cos Cob): Bush-Holley House, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Guilford
    - 84 Boston Street: "Hyland" House, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 85 Boston Road: Thomas Burgis House, Circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Additional material (original), 1989 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Additional material (use copy) (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Oversized material, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 6 Broad Street: Caleb Stone House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Oversized material, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 77 Broad Street: Isaac Stow House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - 212 Clapboard Hill Road: Caleb Dudley House, 1764, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 38 Fair Street: Parsonage of the Fourth Society, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 44 Fair Street: Noah Hodgkin, Sr. House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Oversized material, Circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 58 Fair Street: Nathaniel Johnson House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Oversized material, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 78 Fair Street: Joseph Chittenden House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 16)
        Material restricted until January 1, 2067 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Oversized material, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 575 Leete's Island Road: Pelatiah Leete House, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Oversized material, Circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1 North Street: Captain Samuel Lee House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - 37 Park Street: Heli Hoadley House, 1989
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - 138 State Street: Kingsnorth-Starr House, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 205 State Street: Philo Bishop House, Circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 37 Union Street: The Acadian House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Oversized material, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 25 Water Street: Ebenezer Bartlett House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Oversized material, Circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 54 Water Street: Joseph Parmelee, Jr. House, 1991
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Killingworth, Congregational Church, 1985
    - Original (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Ledyard, 50 Spicer Hill Road, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Litchfield, East Street: John Collins House, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Madison
    - 548 Boston Post Road, Circa 1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 581 Boston Post Road: Deacon John Graves House, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Additional material, 1984, 1988
        - Original (Box 3, Folder 23)
        - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Oversized material, 1987-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Milford
    - 139 North Street, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 34 High Street: Eels-Stowe House, Circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - New Haven
    - General, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Additional material, 1984-1985
        - Original (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - 8 Academy Street: Samuel Wadsworth House, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1017 Chapel Street: Connecticut Hall, Yale University, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 30 College Street: Bartlett House and related properties, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 149 Elm Street: Stokes Pierpont House, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Additional material, 1986
        - Original (Box 3, Folder 25)
        - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - 325 Lighthouse Road: Pardee Morris House, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 275 Orange Street: William Pinto House, Circa 1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Churches on the Green, 1982, 1985
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Theophilus Eaton House (destroyed before 1730), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - New London
    - 11 Hempstead Street: Hempsted House, 1956-1958, circa 1985 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Oversized material, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - New London County Courthouse, 1986
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Northford
    - Middletown Turnpike: Benjamin Houde House, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Old Evarts Tavern (destroyed; 1920?), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Ridgefield
    - 132 Main Street: Keeler Tavern, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Additional material, 1981-1988
        - Original (Box 3, Folder 28)
        - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - West Hartford, General, 1974-1985 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - West Haven, Thomas Painter House (moved to Litchfield), Circa 1980s (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Wethersfield
    - 249 Broad Street: Buttolph-Williams House, 1987
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 29)
      - Oversized material, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 481 Main Street: George Hubbard House, 1987 December 10; 1 (Box 4)
      Interview with the Courchaines (property owners).
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - 527 Main Street: Bennezer Hale House (also known as John Latimer House and Theodore Hale House), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Woodbridge
    - 1907 Litchfield Turnpike: Darling House, 1985
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Woodbury
    - 30 Hollow Road: Jabez Bacon House, 1978
      - Original (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Use copy (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - 149 Hollow Road: Glebe House, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Hopkinton, Massachusetts: Phipps Farmhouse, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified drawings, oversized, 1987, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)